J.M. McIsaac Papers 1888-1973 approximately 1888-1973
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
J.M. McIsaac Papers
approximately 1888-1973
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham 98225-9123 cpnws@wwu.edu
McIsaac, J. M.
XOE_CPNWS0362
0.5 linear feet 1 box
A collection of papers documenting aspects of the life, family and business interests of J.M. (John Malcolm) McIsaac (1860-1941), long-time resident of Spokane, Washington.
A collection of papers documenting aspects of the life, family and business interests of J.M. (John Malcolm) McIsaac (1860-1941), long-time resident of Spokane, Washington. The collection includes brief genealogical materials regarding the McIsaacs, copies of biographical information about J.M. McIsaac, and a variety of mining and other stock certificates, property-related records, financial and legal materials relevant to his business interests in and around Spokane. Family and personal papers in the collection include letters written by McIsaac to his daughter Gladys and grandson John (Jack), typed recollections by Gladys of her mother and childhood, plus a small number of family photographs.
J.M. (John Malcolm) McIsaac was born on Prince Edward Island in 1860, and moved to Massachusetts as a child following the death of his parents. Apprenticed as a granite cutter, McIsaac moved west in 1889 to Spokane, Washington, where he worked initially for stone contractor J.B. Bye. Following work in Oregon on the Cascade Locks (where he met and became married to Etta Mary McGrath), McIsaac returned to Spokane, where he resided until his death in 1941. Following Etta Mary's death in 1905, he raised their three surviving children. McIsaac engaged in a wide variety of business ventures, including co-establishment of the firm McKay and McIsaac, property and mining investments, and remodel work on the building later known as the Davenport Hotel. A long-term employee of the City of Spokane Street Department, McIsaac was also active in the Catholic Church and with the Knights of Columbus and the Independent Order of the Foresters.
The collection is open to the public for research.
The collection was donated to the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies by Leslie Hall in 2018.
The Claude C. Hall Papers at the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies (CPNWS) contain related material.
McIsaac, J. M. -- Archives.
Records (Documents); Photographs.
Spokane (Wash.)
- McIsaac genealogical materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Property-related correspondence and papers, approximately 1932-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Stock certificates, approximately 1897-1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Business, financial and legal papers, approximately 1888-1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Family correspondence, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Clippings re: J.M. McIsaac's death, approximately November 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Final papers and legal estate, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- In memorium statements and letters of condolence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Gladys Hall's recollections of mother and years following her mother's death, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Gladys Hall resume, approximately 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photographs, 1898-1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photographs, 1898-1934 (Box 1, Folder 12)